# Ali sarvghad

personal information

Address: 5295 Toscana Way, Unit 712, San Diego, California,

92122

Phone: +17076908092

Email: asarvgha@eng.ucsd.edu

LinkedIn:

https://www.linkedin.com/pub/ali-sarvghad/31/972/2b8

# Objective

My passion is to design and conduct research in the fascinating fields of information visualization, human computer interaction and visual analytics. I am also very enthusiastic about participating in the process of applying research outcome into practice.

#### **EDUCATION**

University of California San Diego

Postdoctoral Researcher 2016 - Present

Supervisor: Dr. Nadir Weibel

University of Victoria

**PhD in Computer 2009-2016** Supervisor: Dr. Melanie Tory

## **Master of Software Engineering 2006-2008**

Postgrad project title: Dynamic Display of Text Using Lexical

Chains

Supervisor: Dr. Albert Yeap

University of Malaya

## B.A. Honors in Computer 2003-2006

University Science Malaysia

## RELATED EXPERIENCE

### Research Assistant, University of Victoria 2009 - 2016

My research focus is on facilitating visual data analysis, and in particular collaborative data analysis. I work on designing and implementing history modules that visually represent accumulated work history. I particularly research novel applications for history that reduces interaction costs by enabling users to more easily recall and review different aspects of their prior work.

## Teaching Assistant, University of Victoria January 2009 – January 2013

Advanced Programing Lab Instructor (Taught students the lab materials and Victoria helped them with lab exercises)

Computer Science Consultant (Helped students from across the department with their course related questions and problems)

### Research Assistant, University of Malaya 2006-2008

I was a member of Artificial Intelligence lab. My research focus was on text visualization. I designed and developed a prototype tool code named Smart View for keyword-based text summarization. SmartView opens a text file, extracts and displays an ordered list of important keywords contained in the file, then allows users to customize and create their own view. My evaluation showed that enabling user to change the view and customized it based on their need was very beneficial.

# Computer programming freelance tutor 2005-2008

Taught Java and C to undergrad students.

### Software Tester, Melaka 2006-2008

Working part-time, tested and debugged software modules written in Java.

### Software Developer, PegahSoft 2000-2002

Contributed to successful development of hakim, an Electronic Health Record (EHR), software

## Domains of professional competency

- Designing and implementing research prototype systems
- Designing and conducting usability and user studies
- Strong knowledge of different data gathering and analysis methods
- Experienced in dissemination of research results
- Strong ability to cooperate and coordinate joint research efforts with academia and industry

- Excellent oral communication skills as a result of tutoring students at university and presenting research at different venues
- Exceptional competency in teamwork. I have been working in close collaboration with my committee and colleges in VisID research group
- Outstanding project and time management. I have been able to successfully plan and timely carry out all my research projects from design to evaluation and dissemination
- Experienced in professionally resolving conflicts with colleagues and students
- Strong knowledge of software development including software architecture design, software development project management, system analysis and design, and software quality and testing
- Programming skills including: Java, C++, C, Javascript, HTML, XML.

# Projects

Visual History for Workflow Schedule 2015
In this project, I designed a history module that keep tracks of changes in a work schedule. A dashboard visualizes the impact of a change in the schedule in terms

of changes KPIs and affected work items according to business logic.

#### Scented View 2013-2014

Based on the outcomes of my research, I designed and implemented a visual data analysis tool for tabular data that tracked and incorporated analysis history information into the interface widgets. This prototype tool provides visual cues into the coverage of both dimension and data space. Preliminary findings of our current user studies show that this tool can noticeably reduce interaction costs by providing such information as part of user interface.

Footprint-I 2012-2013

Designed and implemented Footprint for facilitating asynchronous collaborative visual data analysis. FootPrint provides insight into the depth and breadth of dimension and data space investigation through a number of interactive visual representations of analysis history. Providing awareness of this perspective is critical in a collaborative environment. Such understanding facilitates more efficient continuation/evaluation of analytical work across a group.

## CoSpaces 2010-2011

Participated in designing and implementing a prototype tool for facilitating co-located collaborative visual data analysis on tabletop. CoSpaces enables multiple users to simultaneously work together and create statistical charts. Some main features include the ability to record and keep track of the work by automatically saving charts, and also an embedded note takin mechanism.

#### Smart View 2007-2008

Designed and implemented Smart View, a prototype tool for keyword-based text summarization. SmartView opens a text file, extracts and displays an ordered list of important keywords contained in the file.

#### **PUBLICATIONS AND PAPERS**

Visualizing Dimension Coverage to Support Exploratory Data Analysis
Authors: Ali Sarvghad, Melanie Tory, and Narges Mahyar
TVCG 2016

Exploiting Analysis History to Support Collaborative Data Analysis
Authors: Ali Sarvghad and Melanie Tory
IEEE Graphics Interfaces 2015

Exploiting History to Reduce Interaction Costs in Collaborative Analysis
Authors: Ali Sarvghad and Melanie Tory
VIS 2014, Provenance Workshop
Observations of Record-Keeping in Co-located Collaborative Analysis

Authors: Narges Mahyar, Ali Sarvghad, Melanie Tory, and Tyler

Weeres HICSS 2013

Note Taking in Co-located Collaborative Visual analytics: Analysis of an Observational Study
Authors: Narges Mahyar, Ali Sarvghad and Melanie Tory
Information Visualization Journal 2012

CoSpaces: Workspaces to Support Co-located Collaborative Visual Analytics

Authors: Narges Mahyar, Ali Sarvghad, Melanie Tory, and Tyler

Weeres
Dexies 2011

A closer look at note taking in the co-located collaborative visual analytics process

Authors: Narges Mahyar, Ali Sarvghad and Melanie Tory VAST 2010

Roles of Notes in Co-located Collaborative Visualization," Workshop on Collaborative Visualization on Interactive Surfaces

Authors: Narges Mahyar, Ali Sarvghad and Melanie Tory

CoVis 2009

History Tools for Collaborative Visualization

Authors: Ali Sarvghad, Narges Mahyar and Melanie Tory

CoVis 2009

LANGUAGES

Farsi – native language

English – speak fluently, read and write with proficiency

References

References are available upon request.